XDeej: When people dive into debates about the greatest of all
time in nearly any discipline, those conversations usually
include a lot of the same elements.
There's an argument to be had about impact vs consistency
A conversation that wanes between competitive dominance
and the era in which that dominance was present.
The merits about being a standout star in a league, or bringing
your team with you to win league championships.
Regardless of what your stance on these questions might be,
it's rare for there to be an almost unanimous agreement
when it comes to who is the best... and yet...
When it comes to League of Legends
there really is only one true answer.
Commentator 1 (Yelling): "FAKER!"
Commentator 2: "Faker with the stop!"
Commentator 3: "It seems like death may have arrived
and his name... is Faker"
XDeej: While his greatness can't be denied, his incredible skill
and numerous championships only provide the foundation for
the story at the heart of his legacy.
While he would use brute force and skill to rise to the top
He would also eventually fall far enough that many wondered if
he would ever truly return to the peak of that summit.
So, join me on the deep dive as we look into how the 'unkillable
demon king' was eventually slain, and how Faker would rise like
a phoenix from the ashes.
[Opening notes of "Phoenix" play]
In 2009, League of Legends is released to the world
and only 18 short months later the game's popularity would
propel it into a global phenomenon.
While its impact would be felt worldwide, it would take deep
root in the Eastern market of Korea and eventually find its way
into the hands of a young teen who enjoyed playing games
with his father and friends.
However, he quickly realized that playing games with his father
in casual matches wasn't going to maintain a
challenge for very long.
And in the span of just a couple years, he had gone from being
afraid to play ranked matches, to the number one ranked player
in all of Korea.
And it wasn't long after that the professional league would come
calling, and the newly labeled Faker... would answer.
Commentator: "Oh look at the cleanse, look at the moves.
Faker! What was that!?
Commentator 2: "Finds them all!"
Commentator 3: "He's gonna go down, Faker picks up the kill!"
Commentator 4: "Faker gets the last laugh"
Commentors Overlapping: "Oh he did it! He's so sick!
"Punches in, she's dead!"
Commentator 5: "Oh my god"
Commentator 1: "Ohhhh, wow!"
Commentator 6: "Fakerrrrrr!!!"
Commentator 1: "Can you say GG"
Commentator: "He might be just the best mid-laner in the world"
XDeej: In his first season with SKT T1, faker had what is
arguably the best rookie season of any player in the
competitive league, even to this day.
Securing a third-place finish in the spring stage,
an MVP nod and international championship
title during the Summer stage, and from there
He'd go on to lead his team to a world championship victory
all within the first seven months of professional play.
But for a player like Faker, these accomplishments would
merely set the stage for what would prove to be only the very
beginnings of the greatest competitor to ever play the game.
After his breakout rookie season, Faker would continue his
dominance into 2014 by taking home wins at the Paris All-star
invitational and the NLB Spring Championship.
But that's when he really got started, as he would lead T1
to take both the spring and summer championships in 2015
followed by back to back world championship wins.
But unfortunately for Faker, he would soon learn...
That nothing lasts forever.
[waning violin note lingers]
2017 would see T1 continue to assert their supremacy in the
LCK, finishing the spring stage with an impressive record
of 16-2 before going on to win the Spring split championship.
But of their two losses, one would come at the hands of a
surprisingly scrappy Samsung Galaxy.
A relatively new team to the competitive scene, this team
was made up of an assortment of strong players including
Ambition, and Ruler, who would go on to be Faker's other half in
what is considered by many to be one of the biggest rivalries
in all of Esports.
While this junior team was coming together and proving it had
what it takes to compete, there was never any serious
consideration that they could contend with the power of T1.
However, when Samsung Galaxy went on an absolute tear
through regional qualifiers, group stages, and then the playoffs,
fate decided that speculation simply wasn't good enough.
[♫ heavy drum intro from "Awaken" ♫]
Commentator: "Game 1 of the 2017 League of Legends
world championship final"
Commentator 2: "Samsung Galaxy only give up one
turret this entire game
and absolutely dominate SK Telecom!
Commentator 3: "So insane from Samsung!
There was so much damage coming in!"
Commentator 2: "Samsung Galaxy retake *another* game!"
Commentator 2: "And he blows up Bang! That's a..."
Commentator 3: "There supposed to lose these team fights,
yet they turn it around!"
Commentator 2: "Do you have what it takes to win the game!?
Ruler, on the nexus!
The upset is complete as the kills come through!"
XDeej: In a best of five match, to determine the best
team in the world, it only took three games.
With such a blowout, many wondered what this meant
for the future of T1.
Commentator 2: "The SKT dynasty is over!
All hail the new kings!"
[metal door slide rolling]
[door slams shut]
['Bang' speaking Korean.]
[Faker's Father speaking Korean.]
XDeej: Faker didn't know it at the time, but he lost far more than
a game that day. During the off-season, his teammates Peanut
and Huni would be let go and they would be followed shortly
thereafter by the head coach, cCarter.
While the loss of any seasoned players is likely to have a huge
impact on a team, 2018 at least held the modest silver lining of
the assistant coach Kkoma being moved up to the top spot
in the coaching lineup.
And despite a focused and dedicated effort from the new coach,
and as talented as their new roster was on paper,
2018 would see T1's misfortune continue to mount.
The spring season would see them saddled with a fourth place
start, and the spring stage playoffs would see them eliminated
after just the second round.
From there they would miss MSI entirely, slip to seventh
in the summer stage, and the team that had won 3 of the last 4
world championships wouldn't even be
competing in worlds at all this year.
Commentator: "Everyone in the Nexel Arena, and you in the chat
were there when the dream died for SK Telecom T1.
The question finally has an answer, can SKT still make worlds?
Sadly, the answer is no. The era is over."
XDeej: Despite the doubters, T1 would show signs of life in
2019 by taking the spring split championship.
They'd go on to place fourth at MSI, and amazingly, win the
summer split championship as well.
Unfortunately, when they got to worlds, they would fall short of
victory once more, being eliminated in the semi-finals.
While coming close and stumbling at the last hurdle would be
enough to show improvement on the previous year,
it wouldn't be enough to live up to the legacy that
was expected of Faker and T1.
And just like his big losses from the last two years,
Faker would lose more than just a championship.
Serving as the figure head of the organization,
the father figure and protector when Faker was far from home,
and the most decorated coach in the history of the league,
2019 would also take Kkoma as well.
[Coach Kkoma speaking Korean.]
[Suspenseful rhythmic violins play]
[soft choral notes drift into silence]
XDeej: 2020 saw T1 fall into familiar form,
With Faker leading the way to a strong start in spring,
Winning the spring stage championship,
and then beginning to struggle in the summer.
Shortly thereafter, and for only the third time in the franchise's
history, T1 would then fail to qualify for the worlds tournament.
At this point, questions began to emerge about whether or not
Faker was truly as good as people thought.
And going into the 2021 season, Faker was now 25 years old
in a league where its most competitive superstars
were still in their teens.
With Faker slowly gaining the perception of a great player
that was simply no longer able to deliver a world championship,
Faker knew the pressure was on to deliver, and a strong
showing at worlds was an absolute must.
Commentator: "It will be an amazing semi-final.
Damwon Kia going toe to toe with T1
The best right now, versus the best that ever was."
"But Khan will drop for first blood. Faker picking up the kill."
Commentator 2: "Canyon turns it back and it's disaster for T1!"
Commentator 1: "Damwon Kia, they're going in. Gumayusi now
going down. Canna forced to back away.
Keria and Faker just getting torn apart!
[♫ and we'll burn it all down ♫]
Commentator: Faker over the wall, 16...
Commentator 2: "Oh my god he gets it Oner!"
Commentator 1: Damwon Kia getting routed in the river but
Canyon still standing strong for a moment? No.
Double! Triple for Gumayusi!
Showmaker wants to make a play but NOT TODAY!
Sit down Showmaker this is T1's time!
XDeej: After going even on games, Faker would look to put the
team on his back and went on an absolute onslaught of diving
headlong into the enemy team to secure incredible kills that
would turn the tide in crucial fights to claim victory in game 3.
Recognizing that if you want to wear the crown,
you have to go through the king,
Damwon would adapt their strategy to target Faker early, and
often. With Faker often falling to mobs of enemies Damwon
would strike back to take game 4 in decisive fashion.
Commentator: "Who else to push them to a game 5"
XDeej: And in a final and deciding game 5,
T1 would once again find history repeating itself.
Commentator: "Not the next Faker! Showmaker!
Damwon Kia will not be stopped!
Damn old legends and old legacies.
Goodbye Faker! Goodbye T1! Hello Damwon and Showmaker!
They will defend their title!"
XDeej: Beyond the pain and frustration of losing,
there was something about this match that
made it even harder for Faker.
[Coach Kkoma Speaking Korean.]
XDeej: And with that,
many T1 fans simply assumed that that was it.
While he remained an extremely skilled player,
the sun had set on Faker's career
and a world championship just wasn't in the cards anymore.
But, rather than to prove the doubters wrong, Faker
entered the 2022 season with something to prove to himself.
And the rest of T1 would rise to the challenge.
[♫ opening thrum of "Blood, Sweat, and Tears" ♫]
T1 wouldn't just start spring strong
They would achieve a historic accomplishment
by going 18-0 for the spring stage.
And then adding to their dominance by remaining undefeated
on their way to the spring split championship.
While they would taste their first defeat of 2022
in the mid-season invitational
They would still offer a stellar performance by
falling just shy of victory and taking second in the tournament.
From there, they would offer a 15-3 effort in the summer,
and once again fall just short of ultimate victory
in the finals to a strong Gen.G team led by their
rising superstar Chovy, and their pickup of Faker's long-time
rival and legendary bot-laner in Ruler.
While it's true they didn't maintain first place in every split
or tournament that they entered
It was still extremely clear that T1 was in top form.
So, when the 20-18 DRX went on a Cinderella run to ultimately
end up facing them in the grand finals, T1 had every reason
to believe that it was finally their time to return to the throne.
[Oner speaking Korean.]
XDeej: T1 might not have known it at the time,
but they would learn that there is no poison
more insidious than hubris.
[Multiple people speaking Korean in T1's pre-game huddle]
It was T1.
A titan.
A dynasty.
A team that had won more than twice as many
matches going into the finals as DRX
No one gave them a chance to emerge victorious.
So it was no surprise when T1
took the first match in decisive fashion.
Unwilling to roll over and die, DRX would then strike back
by taking the second match to tie the series.
And defying all odds, T1 and DRX would then trade the next 2
to tie the series going into the final deciding match.
With the series tied at match point, Gumayusi would come up
with a huge play that would provide T1 an opportunity to launch
an attack at DRX's base.
Unfortunately, DRX would be waiting there to defend,
and the attack would fail.
But in doing so, it allowed DRX to launch an attack of their own.
[escalating noise of a Nexus being destroyed]
[transition into "Ashes and Blood"]
[♫ To ashes and blood ♫]
[♫ hey ♫]
Commentator: "They're done!"
Commentator: "Champions"
Commentator: "The new kings!"
[♫ Opening piano notes of "I Can't Hear it Now" ♫]
[Keria speaking Korean.]
After facing such a crushing end during a year
where they were expected to win,
morale was low going into the 2023 season.
While Faker's competitive edge gave him no choice but to march
forward, 2023 would prove to be just as challenging a year
as the few before it.
But this time, it would prove difficult
for entirely different reasons.
As casters, players, and fans dissected Faker's
future potential in the league,
Fate laid out a challenge for him
that would allow him one final test.
In order to move forward,
Faker would have to go back,
and do battle with his past.
[♫ soft rhythmic piano notes trail into silence ♫]
2023 would start with Faker returning to the previous summer
to avenge the loss against Gen.G when they met again
in the spring championship finals.
Only instead of facing Chovy and Ruler,
it would be Chovy and his old teammate Peanut
that would edge out a victory against T1.
As a poetic twist, his old teammate Huni,
who played with T1 the last time Faker and Peanut
were together, oversaw the match as a commentator.
From there, the mid-season invitational saw Faker in a
showdown that went all the way to game 5. Where his old rival
Ruler lined up across from him with his new team of JDG.
Despite a good showing, they would once again fall to the
mounting pressure, and be eliminated in the semi-finals.
Going back to the summer split, then worlds 2022,
the previous spring, and now MSI,
this would mark the fourth championship tournament
in a row that T1 would fail to secure a victory.
But as difficult as the season had been for Faker thus far,
it was nothing compared to what he would deal with next.
[Faker's father speaking Korean.]
XDeej: 10 years of competing at the highest level
had taken its toll.
And now, one of Faker's most important tools,
was starting to fail him.
[Faker speaking Korean.]
Even with Faker's incredible competitive drive,
the problem would only get worse.
And after conversations with his team and coaches,
the decision was made.
Faker was placed on medical leave,
and for the first time in 845 days,
Faker would not join his team on stage.
[♫ dramatic violin begins ♫]
Filling in for Faker would be an untested rookie
from T1's training league by the name of Poby.
Interestingly, Poby would be looking to fill the biggest shoes
in the entirety of the league at the same age Faker was
when he played his first match nearly a decade ago.
While Poby was supported by a lineup that had proven that they
had what it takes to win, and had a lot of skill in his own right,
he simply wasn't Faker.
And the results made it clear how big
the gap between them actually was.
Commentator: "Faker did get injured,
they are on a 4 loss streak."
[♫ Violin music intensifies with added horns ♫]
XDeej: Though Faker's condition remained an unknown...
One thing was absolutely clear...
If T1 wanted a shot to qualify for worlds,
they were gonna need their superstar in the lineup to do it.
In what was originally thought to be a 12-week
break to allow him to recover,
Faker would return to the lineup in just 31 days.
[♫ Opening notes of "Dynasties and Dystopia" play ♫]
XDeej: After finishing summer with a 9-9 record,
T1 clawed their way through the summer playoffs
for a last-chance effort to secure a spot at worlds.
Standing in their way was KT Rolster
A long-time LCK rival and a heavy 10-4
favorite for their all or nothing matchup.
While everyone knew that T1 didn't stand a chance,
it seems like no one remembered to tell Faker.
Commentator: "And T1 they don't even need
a baron to win this game."
Commentator 2: "Faker has just avoided death"
Commentator 1: "The stun's not gonna work,
the cleanse is beautiful."
Commentator 3: "And this is just what Faker does."
Commentator 1: "Every carry on T1 is massive
and Zeus will get the last one AGAIN!"
"It does not matter, Gumayusi grabs the double!
The Nexus turrets will be taken out,
and T1 will deny the reverse sweep!
And they'll qualify for the world championship!"
After a relatively unimpressive season,
Faker missing a whole month due to injury
and almost everyone believing they didn't
have a shot at winning in the finals.
T1 had somehow earned just enough
points to keep their hopes alive.
[♫ Soft dramatic strings begin playing ♫]
While T1 had managed to sneak their way into the playoffs
for worlds, the path they now had to walk to get to the top
looked impossible.
Of the 4 LPL Chinese teams in the tournament,
you had BLG, who had never lost a best of 5 to T1...
Ever.
And constantly battling them for second place was Weibo,
one of the strongest in the LPL.
And then there was the new home of his rival Ruler in JDG,
who were currently in the process of trying to complete what is
referred to as the golden road.
An accomplishment that requires a team to win the spring, MSI,
and summer championships.
The heavy favorite now only need a win at worlds
to complete the historic achievement.
But before Faker could rewrite any of *those* histories,
he had to go back to better times to face his former teammate
and protegé in Scout.
Who is now not only looking to add to his world championship,
but looking to leave Faker's shadow behind for good.
And to add just a little more pressure
to an already impossible situation,
by the time their match with LNG was set to begin,
the other two Korean teams in the tournament,
that T1 had already lost to this season,
were out...
Leaving T1 as the sole remaining Korean team left.
And with that,
The hopes of a nation...
Rested on the shoulders of T1.
[♫ Opening notes of "Gods" plays] ♫]
Commentator: "For T1, the task ahead of them is absolutely
monumental. ONLY LPL teams, starting with LNG today,
and if you get through that well then you get to play JDG,
so it's just insane!"
Commentator 2: "Gumayusi ascending to godhood
in that moment as LNG are torn to shreds!"
"And now WHAT THE HELL!?"
"Will it be enough to lock down Zeus? No is the answer!"
"Scout given to the Aatrox as tribute!"
"They see the weakness in the armor of LNG,
and they tear it asunder!"
"They remain composed, they close out cleanly
and bring us to match point."
"The team falls away... Faker STAYS STANDING!
T1 STAYS STANDING!"
"The last light of the LCK burns bright
as they head to the semi-finals!"
As T1 celebrated, and rightfully so,
they had to temper their excitement.
as they had an absolute monster
of an opponent in front of them.
JDG was still looking to pave the golden road,
and would undoubtedly be paying close
attention to their opposition.
Gamayusi made sure to use the opportunity
to send a message.
[Gamayusi speaking Korean.]
[Interviewer and crowd cheer loudly]
and with that, the stage was set.
T1 was 3 wins away from returning to the world's finals,
and all that stood between them and their second chance
at victory was one more ghost from Faker's past.
Commentator: "The infernal chain, looking for the lock up!
Oner immediately with the follow up engage
But now they are just fish, caught in the barrel
T1 stepping in, and dominating the herald fight!"
"The lock up there from Guma from so far away
"Oner coming in. The fall back onto
missing trying not to stick around for too long
One taken down already,
Knight now going in trying to turn it back.
Guma says 'NOT TODAY'"
"That's a clean ace, that's got to be the game.
I think they can push for the end!"
"The Nexus, lower and lower
T1 drawing first blood in this series!"
XDeej: After taking the first game, T1 and JDG would then
trade the next 2, putting T1 ahead on match point.
Going into game 4, Ruler could feel the championship
slipping through his fingers.
The golden road about to come to an end.
But in hindsight, he should have known better.
All of Ruler's roads, golden or not
Always led back to Faker.
Commentator: "T1 just need to weather the storm"
"TP coming in, Faker looking to make the
play and he gets Ruler! Oner goes in!"
Commentator 1: "T1,
Commentator 1: "T1, in the clutch,
Commentator 2: "what"
Commentator 1: "T1, in the clutch, are too damn clean!"
"They've taken down BLG, they've taken down LNG
It is not LPL versus LCK
It is T1 versus the LPL
and they like those odds!"
XDeej: They had beaten old rivals, they had halted construction
on the golden road, and they had scraped and clawed for every
step they took beyond the heartbreak of the previous year.
Now,
just one match stood between Faker
and his redemption.
Commentator: "Welcome everyone to the League of Legends
2023 worlds final live from the Gocheok skydome
in Seoul South Korea.
[Gamayusi speaking Korean.]
XDeej: Even for a quiet team, T1 was abnormally
quiet on the drive in to the venue.
They could have been simply trying to focus.
Or perhaps, they were saving everything
they wanted to say... for the stage.
Commentator: "And we are just moments away
from getting onto the rift."
Commentator 2: "Game number 1 is upon us"
XDeej: 7 years since his last, and 10 years since his first
And the only time he'd ever play for a championship
on his native soil
The eyes of a nation fell on Faker,
for what was thought to be his last dance.
Commentator: "Worlds 2023, game... number... 1"
"No worries there at all as Crisp is under the turret
they throw down barrel,
but Zeus is down too! With the ultimate-Light...
goes down so low, but isn't going to survive!
Weiwei trying, and I think T1 are just gonna end game 1 here."
"And here we are, into game number 2"
"They have a turret here, the charm, he's going to split them...
Keria tries to get in the...
He goes forward and then just explodes!
And then Oner, thinks that that's his moment
and it's a double AGAIN!"
XDeej: In a best of 5 match, to determine the best team
in the world, it only took 3 games.
Commentator: "He likes this one though, 1 versus 3,
he's absorbing so much, the Emperor's Divide!
It comes in but he's STILL ALIVE!
What is going on!? Faker tidies up
The burst! Everyone's just exploding!
And Weiwei trying to get something done but it does not matter,
T1 are too strong!"
[Oner speaking Korean.]
[Faker speaking Korean.]
[♫ Oh pick yourself up cause, Legends Never Die ♫]
Commentator: "The SKT legacy has been reignited!"
[♫ Can you hear them screaming out ♫]
Commentator: "T1 will be your 2023 world champions!"
[♫ Legends never die ♫]
[♫ They become a part of you ♫]
[♫ Any time you bleed for reaching greatness ♫]
[♫ Legends never die ♫]
[♫ rhythmic piano notes slowly grow silent ♫]
XDeej: That would be an incredible end to an amazing journey,
if that were the end.
Instead, in 2024,
Faker would put it all on the line once more.
Even with nothing left to prove,
Even with no challenge left to overcome,
and going against former teammates,
historic rivals,
and rising dynasties,
Faker would go on to claim MVP honors
while bringing home his fifth world championship.
As of the time of this video, Faker has made no mention
of his intent to retire...
And going into the 2025 season,
I know that I, along with many others,
will be cheering him on,
in the hopes that he somehow manages
to pull off the impossible...
Again...
[♫ Banjo strumming from "Spin the Wheel" fades in ♫]"
Being one of the greatest off all time
and performing at an absolute peak, means many of you
probably already knew Faker's story.
But if I did a good job, hopefully you understand now that
That resilience, dedication, and mental toughness,
were just as much part of that journey as his overall skill.
Please make sure to like and subscribe if you enjoyed the video,
and until I see you next time...
Party on
[♫ And if you love the journey more than the end. Go ahead. ♫]
[♫ Just turn that hourglass around and count to ten. ♫]
[♫ This aint goodbye, no more. ♫]
[♫ Nah... It just began ♫]
Faker: "Thank you for watching."